Carolyn Gabel-Brett Feminist and LGBT Collections. GLBTQ.2012.03
GLBTQ Archives
Carolyn Gabel-Brett Feminist and LGBT Collections
1986-2009
GLBTQ.2012.03
GLBTQ Archives
9.0 Linear feet
Carolyn Gabel-Brett was an avid activist for women’s rights, gender equality and homosexual rights, participating in several Connecticut groups since 1972. This collection includes materials from her endeavors from 1986 through 2009 including documents, periodicals, and photographs regarding local and national events, community projects, and legislation pertaining to gender and homosexual rights.
Gabel-Brett, Carolyn
Biographical/Historical note
Carolyn Gabel-Brett was a feminist activist in Connecticut since she moved here in 1972. She worked in women’s reproductive rights for over ten years including establishing the Connecticut chapter of the National Abortion Rights Action League (NARAL). She was on the faculty of the University Of Connecticut School Of Social Work where she coordinated a project on violence against women. She was one of the founders and long-time co-manager of the Reader's Feast, Hartford's feminist, progressive bookstore café for 12 years. She joined with Miles Rapoport in founding Democracy Works in 1999. She retired as Executive Director of Democracy Works in 2003. Carolyn has been an out lesbian activist serving in leadership positions in the CT Stonewall Foundation and the Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Civil Rights. She was an active Board member of Latinos/as Contra SIDA for six years. She continues to work with Love Makes a Family fighting for full marriage equality in Connecticut. Carolyn and her partner, Leslie, have been together for 25 years and have three adult children. The Connecticut Women’s Education And Legal Fund (CWEALF) was incorporated in 1973, being one of the oldest women’s organizations in the country. The group is dedicated to empowering women, girls and their families in the Greater Hartford area. They provide a toll free helpline to refer attorneys or obtain a free legal information booklet, training, technical assistance and resources to employers, schools, and community organizations concerning gender equality and legal rights of individuals. They seek to improve laws and policies affecting women, girls and their families, child support programs, and hate crimes prevention programs. Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights (CCLGCR) was formed during the summer of 1983 by a group of gay men and women discouraged by the continued defeat of the Gay Civil Rights Bill. They decided to form a statewide organization dedicated to the passage of civil rights legislation regarding discrimination based on sexual orientation. The coalition worked with progressive political organizations, other minority groups, religious affiliates, educators, and legal, social, and healthcare professionals to develop a lesbian and gay community. In 1985 the group established four regions throughout the state. In 1986, the group added “Connecticut” to the beginning of their name, becoming the CT CLGCR, in order to be able to back political candidates according to state law. The Political Action Committee was thus formed in 1988. The PAC interviewed candidates and reported the information back to the coalition, focusing mainly on areas of importance for homosexuals. The establishment of the PAC also led to inclusion in the statewide Legislative Electoral Action Program (LEAP), strengthening the CT CLGCR’s voice in the state government. In 1989, the group organized the HIV Task Force which was created to deal with legislative issues involving HIV and AIDS by writing position papers and making suggestions to the rest of the coalition. Another project was called The Anti-Violence Project, following the murder of a Connecticut gay man in 1988. Immediately following this incident, the AVP was created to monitor the murder case but also created Speak Out! in 1989. This program supplied organizations, school, and other interested parties with a participating speaker on homosexual issues. They also focused on the Hate Crimes Bill in 1990 pushing for its passage in conjunction with several other groups. The Religious Task Force was created in 1991 to organize the state’s religious community in support of the Gay Rights Bill. Later, the group changed its name to include transgender individuals, becoming CCLGBTCR. By 1999, the group was organized in six congressional districts and supported issues in the legislature such as anti-discrimination laws for students K-12, private right of action, health issues support such as HIV/AIDS and breast cancer, domestic partner benefits for state employees, and opposition to any state law prohibiting same gender marriage. In 2000, CCLGBTCR embarked on the Diversity Project to expand the membership base by meeting with diverse communities in the state, raise the level of awareness for the coalition, and assist communities in overcoming barriers that hinder their participation in the work of the coalition. The Stonewall Congress was formed to protect and advocate the health, safety, and civil rights of the lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender communities. This group formed in 1995 as a network of diverse organizations and individuals. It was managed by a Steering Committee and included special task forces working on specific issues. Often the Stonewall Congress worked in conjunction with other groups on special projects.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains materials related to several gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender civil rights and pride groups in Connecticut from 1986 to 2009. This includes Connecticut P.r.i.d.e., Connecticut Women’s Education and Legal Fund, Family Pride, Gay & Lesbian Parents Coalition International, The Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights, and The Connecticut Stonewall Coalition. Issues discussed include hate crimes legislation, gay marriage, gay civil rights, and domestic partner rights. The range of materials include correspondence, newspaper articles, magazine articles, meeting minutes, agendas, budgets, flyers, and photographs.
Oral history interview
An oral history interview of Carolyn Gabel-Brett is available within the Digital Collections of the GLBTQ Archives. http://content.library.ccsu.edu/cdm/landingpage/collection/GLBTQ
AIDS (Disease) -- Law and legislation -- Connecticut; AIDS activists; Brett, Leslie; Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights; Connecticut Stonewall Foundation; Connecticut Women's Educational and Legal Fund; Connecticut Women's Political Caucus; Democracy Works; Family violence -- Connecticut; Feminism.; Gay and lesbian studies; Gay couples -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Gay liberation movement -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Gay rights -- United States -- History; Hate crimes -- Connecticut -- Legislative history; Homosexuality -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- Periodicals; Homosexuality -- Connecticut -- Periodicals; Homosexuality -- Families; Homosexuality -- Law and legislation -- United States -- Periodicals; Lamont, Ned, 1954-; Latinos/as Contra SIDA (Latinos/as Against AIDS); Lesbians -- Connecticut; Love Makes a Family; Marriage law -- Connecticut; Rapoport, Miles S.; Reproductive health -- Connecticut; Same-sex marriage -- Connecticut; Social work education; United Way of Connecticut; University of Connecticut, School of Social Work; West Hartford (Conn.); Wollenberg, William L.; Women -- Violence against -- Connecticut; Women's rights -- Connecticut
- Series I: Personal and Women's Issues
  - Carolyn Gabel-Brett - resume and job applications, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Carolyn Gabel-Brett - correspondence, 1976, 1985, 1999, 2002-2003, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence - Carolyn Gabel-Brett and Frank Gagliardi, 2002-2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carolyn Gabel-Brett - Resume, "Profile in Metroline, 2000, newspaper articles about Leslie Gabel-Brett 2006, 2000, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Carolyn Gabel-Brett - CT Judicial Training, 1998-2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carolyn Gabel-Brett - Testimony before the Judiciary Committee in support of Acts concerning Marriage Equality and Recognition, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Civil Marriage Collaborative - notes from meetings, minutes, funds, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family Protection Act - fact sheet, petition (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Child Welfare - newsletters, conference brochure, 1980, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Family Pride, Gay and Lesbian Parents Coalition International - correspondence, articles, conference announcements, newsletter, "In the Family: The Magazine of Lesbians, Gays, Bisexuals and their Relations", 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Family Diversity Project - "Love Makes a Family" Photo/Text Exhibit, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Family Pride Coalition - "The Family Tree" newsletter, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Connecticut Voices for Children - brochure on poverty, "Special Report on Growing up Healthy", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Casey Family Programs - Family Diversity Projects Photo/Text Exhibit, correspondence regarding gay/lesbian foster parents, Sexual Orientation Diversity Training, "Present Tense...Future Perfect"-Rubber Duck Production, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - National Youth Advocacy Coalition - advocacy workshop, n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Connecticut Women's Agenda - legislative priorities, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Council of Women's Organizations - CT Brigade in Tampa, FL canvassing project, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Equality Federation - conference, case studies, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - New England Women's Musical Retreat (NEWMR VII) - program and directory of craftswomen, September 4-7, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Women's Issues in Lilith, The Jewish Women's Magazine, no. 7, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Religious Liberty Protection Act (RLPA) - newspaper article, correspondence, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rainbow Interfaith Covenant and Outreach - correspondence, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - West Hartford Interfaith Coalition (WHIC) Planning Group - agendas, minutes, correspondence, notes, fact sheets, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - West Hartford Interfaith Coalition (WHIC), Community Housing Development Organization, Women, Infants, Children - MLS listings, outline, notes, phone list, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - West Hartford Gay Lesbian, Bisexual, and Transgender Teens - newspaper articles, support groups, handwritten notes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - West Hartford Community Television - Women's Perspective: the Personal is Political, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Joe Steffan, West Hartford Town Council Candidate - newspaper articles, campaign materials, other candidates, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Connecticut Association for Human Services (CAHS) - newsletter, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Governor's Task Force on Racial Harmony: A Status Report, March 9, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - YWCA nominating committee - minutes, notes, contact information, correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - March on Washington - official program, map, article, Washington Blade Special Edition for the 1993 National March on Washington [issue relocated to periodical collection] (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Human Rights Campaign Fund - job discrimination, political information, brochure, newsletter, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Community Foundation Project - partners, workshops for nonprofits, handwritten notes, grant information, "Funders of Lesbian, Gay, and Bisexual Programs", 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Safe and Affirming Network for Education (SANE) - organization information, fact sheet, meeting notes, newspaper article, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - List of proposals for grants, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Connecticut Immigrant and Refugee Coalition "Immigrants in Connecticut: An Unrecognized Asset" - agenda, conference materials, notes, fact sheets about immigration policy, State Capitol Building, January 30, 2004; articles from the Urban Institute about children of immigrants, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Responsible Individuals Striving Everyday - Rise-Zine, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Connecticut Power Group - correspondence about previous meeting, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - National Lesbian Conference, Atlanta, GA - mailings, Connecticut Coalition News, April 24-28, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Connecticut P.R.I.D.E - brochure, event advertising, Pride Day programs, 1993, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Connecticut P.R.I.D.E - Gay and Lesbian Art Exhibition program, Pridefest Art Exhibition Committee correspondence, newspaper article about Pride Parade in Hartford, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - OutWrite: National Lesbian and Gay Writers Conference - programs, brochures, 1995, 1996, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - News articles/media regarding GLBTQ and religion, family, the arts, politics, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Resource Guide for Gay Connecticut - compiled by the Gay Men's Chorus, September 1994 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - National Lesbian Action Foundation-ASTRAEA - correspondence, advertisements, Lesbian Writers Fund Gala program, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Clinton/Gore 1996 - "A Record of Respecting Gay and Lesbian Americans" (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Metroline magazine, 1996-1997; pages from Metroline, 1998 all regarding GLBTQ issues, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Gay and Lesbian Advocates and Defenders - news releases, correspondence, newsletters, year-end briefs, 1997-2000 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gay and Lesbian Health Collective, Hartford, Women's Advisory Committee - correspondence, events, "The Collective" newsletter, survey, newspaper articles, request for proposal, handwritten notes, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Gay Lesbian Straight Education Network (GLSEN) Connecticut - correspondence, advertisements for events, 1997-1999, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - International Gay and Lesbian Human Rights Commission - annual reports, 1998-2001; newsletter, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Queer Alliance, Wesleyan University - correspondence, contacts, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Queer and Active - electronic mailings; Connecticut Stonewall Foundation - conference, advertisement, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Connecticut Gay and Lesbian Film Festival - pamphlets, schedule, program, June 4-12, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force "Creating Change" conference, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Names Project, AIDS Memorial Quilt, Washington, DC, 1992; The National Museum of Women in the Arts exhibit, 1992/1993 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Connecticut HIV/AIDS Action Council - conference program, action alerts, 1993, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Connecticut AIDS Action Council - newsletters, articles, AIDS Awareness Day agenda, correspondence, fact sheets, 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Material separated (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Series II: Women's Health and Women's Rights
  - Domestic abuse, battered women - articles, publications, mailings, 1979-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Domestic Abuse research - papers, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Connecticut Task Force on Abused Women - meeting minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sexual abuse within families - fact sheets, brochures, checklist, papers, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Women's Health Network - newsletters, alerts, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hartford Interval House for Battered Women - brochures, pamphlets, training materials, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Violence against women - articles, newsletters, correspondence, National Coalition Against Domestic Violence material, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Connecticut Task Force on Abused Women - fact sheet, funding report, racism awareness, Domestic Violence in CT paper, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Women's Health Services - newsletters, mailings, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Connecticut Task Force on Abused Women - brochures, flyers, correspondence, questionnaires, membership application, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Connecticut Alliance of Sexual Assault Services - correspondence, agendas, minutes, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Coalition Against Domestic Violence "End Violence in the Lives of Women" - conference materials, information, August 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - University of Connecticut: President's Committee on Violence Against Women - final report, December 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Connecticut Task Force on Abused Women legislative committee - agendas, forms, minutes, flyers, notes, legislation, job description, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Advisory Committee on Violence Against Women - status report, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Women's Health aFair Conference, domestic violence information - fact sheets, support group information, definitions, notes, newsletters, articles, reports, correspondence, April 1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Women's Health aFair Conference, Domestic Violence Workshop - fact sheets, correspondence, notes, forms, articles, April 1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Hartford Interval House Shelter - forms, flyers, handouts, phone lists, newsletter, fact sheets, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Victim Advocate Volunteer Training Workshop - training test, agenda, forms, notes, organizational chart, fact sheets, January 1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Connecticut Coalition Against Domestic Violence (CCADV) Training Coordinator - correspondence, job description, presentation skills information, September 1998 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Permanent Commission on the Status of Women (PCSW) - mailings, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Permanent Commission on the Status of Women (PCSW) - meeting minutes, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Connecticut Permanent Commission on the Status of Women (PCSW) "Making Women Visible Day" - flyer, program, fact sheets, sticker, business card, February 1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Connecticut Commission on the Status of Women - Legislative Report, 1997 and 1998; Annual Report, 1998; newsletters, 1998; handwritten notes; "Diversity and the Vote: Lessons for Exploring the Multicultural Dimensions of the Suffrage Movement," 1995, 1995, 1997, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Reproductive rights and abortion - correspondence, fact sheets, brochures, articles, mailings, 1977, 1980, 1981, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Abortion Rights - "Once and for All" conference, Yale Law School, January 22, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Connecticut NARAL (National Abortion Rights Action League) - newsletters, mailings, meeting minutes, vote counts, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - NARAL (National Abortion Rights Action League) - bumper stickers, election material, fact sheets, events, Roe v. Wade anniversary activities, "A State by State Review of Abortion and Reproductive Rights" Voters' Guide, articles related to abortion legislation, "She had a Name. She Had a Family. She was Leona's Sister Gerri." by Roberta Brandes Gratz in Ms. Magazine 1995-2000, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) - miscellaneous publications, correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) - publications, pamphlets, letters, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - National Organization for Women (CT NOW) Feminist Awards Dinner - articles, 1997, 1999, 2000, 2001, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - National Organization for Women (NOW) 10th Annual Feminist Awards Dinner program - C. Gabel-Brett is recipient of Eleanor Roosevelt Award, March 1998 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Connecticut Women's Educational and Legal Fund (CWEALF) - "Who's Who in the Right Wing" booklet, "Women and their Families" booklet, [1980] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Connecticut Women's Educational and Legal Fund (CWEALF) - "Rape and the Law" booklet, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Connecticut Women's Education and Legal Fund (CWEALF) - Awards Dinner programs, 2000; Connecticut Pridelink, 1998; 25th Anniversary Program, 1998; Newspaper articles, 1997; Legal Rights of Lesbians, Gay Men and Bisexuals in Connecticut, and Legal Rights of Older Women, 1997, 1998, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Family Planning Funding: the Political Process" by Carolyn Gabel Allen, April 25, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Marnie W. Mueller - research papers "Economic Determinants of Volunteer Work by Women," "Occupational Segregation and Volunteer Work", 1975 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Women's Rights - various publications, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Connecticut Coordinating Committee for the National Commission on the Observance of International Women's Year - correspondence, minutes, manual, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Displaced Homemakers in Connecticut - surveys, evaluation of services, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Feminist Press - brochures, announcements, mailings, book lists, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Equal Rights Amendment - clippings, petition, "The Right Connection: A Seminar for Business and Professional Women" report, 1979, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Title IX - summary, "Equals" newsletter, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Human services - mailings, newsletters, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Miscellaneous organizations, 1980, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Women's Studies - newspaper clippings, newsletters, mailings, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Ms. Magazine Calendar in support of the many programs of Project Woman, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "The Dinner Party" Project with Judy Chicago Lecture Series - correspondence, press releases, participants, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Public Affairs [YWCA] - meeting minutes, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Women's Integrating Seminar "Executive Management for Women: A Trainer's Guide," National Board of the YWCA, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Women for Racial and Economic Equality (WREE) - article, agenda, mailing, 1981, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Connecticut Women's Congress - correspondence, minutes, agenda program, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - W.I.N. (Women's Issue Network) Political Action Committee (PAC) - endorsement procedure, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Leslie Brett - research paper "Adding Age to Gender: Some Thoughts on Identity and Social Status in New Guinea", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Connecticut Coalition for Women in Prison - correspondence, statement of accounts, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Feminist issues - related articles, clippings, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Series III: University of Connecticut (UCONN) School of Social Work
  - UCONN - Grant application "Delivery of Family Planning Services" C. Gabel, University Educational Assistant, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - UCONN School of Social Work - articles, 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - UCONN School of Social Work Domestic Abuse Project, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - UCONN School of Social Work Domestic Abuse Project Grant - final report, 1979-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - National Association of Social Workers (NASW) 1st Annual Conference on Social Work Practice with Women - registration, attendees, flyers, notes, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - UCONN School of Social Work - Domestic Abuse Proposal, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - UCONN Women's Center Annual Report, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - UCONN School of Social Work - correspondence, notes, reports, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - New England Regional Child Welfare Training Center, UCONN School of Social Work - work plan for 1981, quarterly report 1980, 1980, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - UCONN School of Social Work - Training about gay and lesbian culture and lifestyle, Title XX, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Title XX Training Grant - report (rough draft), grant summary, questionnaire, correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - UCONN School of Social Work Conference "Sensitivity is Not Enough: Social Service Delivery-Lesbians and Gay Men" - flyer, schedule, forms, handouts, articles, bibliography, correspondence, September 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)